<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter id="DRDilIntroduction"> 
	 <chapterinfo><date role="LastMod">Tuesday, July 13, 2004 13:28:43</date>
	 </chapterinfo>
	 <title>Introduction</title> 
	 <para><?xm-replace_text {Introduction Paragraph}?></para>
	 <para>DIL is an XML application tightly integrated with the Frontend
		  Client. Each element tag of DIL represents a node that is defined in a Frontend
		  Client. So, when you see a <symbol>&lt;checkbox ... &gt;</symbol> tag in an
		  interface document you know that the client has a 
		  <classname>checkbox</classname> node defined to render the DIL element.
		  Properties in the client nodes which may be set are represented as element
		  attributes in DIL. The values attached to the attributes are converted to the
		  appropriate type and assigned to the properties of the client node. </para> 
	 <para>When a DIL element is derived rather than built by hand, the
		  Derivation engine uses the metadata tags described in 
		  <ulink url="DFRTagReference.HTML">Tag Reference</ulink> to generate
		  attributes and values for the client.</para> 
	 <para>Nearly every DIL element has a <symbol>bop:name</symbol> attribute.
		  This is the name used to resolve references to other elements, such as a
		  reference to a source element.</para> 
	 <bridgehead>Empty Interface</bridgehead> 
	 <para>The following is an empty Interface element. The interface may
		  contain exactly one Element node and several action, source, and other
		  non-element nodes. The Designer enforces the rules of ownership/parenthood in
		  DIL. If you have questions about whether a node can appear in a specific
		  location, try out the Designer.</para> 
	 <programlisting>&lt;interface
    xmlns:bop='www.alphora.com/schemas/bop'
    text='form name goes here'
    mainsource='MainSourceName goes here'
&gt;

&lt;/interface&gt;
</programlisting> 
	 <para>The <symbol>xmlns:bop</symbol> declaration provides several services
		  used in converting DIL from a text format to an interactive form. The text
		  attribute provides the title used on the form. The <symbol>mainsource</symbol>
		  attribute provides a global alias to a source defined in the body of the
		  <symbol>interface</symbol>. See the appropriate interface class (listed in the
		  see also section) for more information about the
		  <symbol>interface</symbol>.</para> 
	 <bridgehead>Keyboard Accelerators</bridgehead> 
	 <para>The text/title of nodes may include accelerator hints marked by an
		  ampersand ("&amp;"), but these are considered optional by the client. The
		  Windows client will allocate the requested accelerator hint if available, or
		  assign its own if not available. The Web client currently strips off
		  accelerators.</para> 
	 <bridgehead>Designer Toolbox</bridgehead> 
	 <para>The list of core elements in the toolbox comes from the
		  <filename>nodetype.dnt</filename> file.</para> 
	 <para>If you extend DIL by adding controls and their corresponding Frontend
		  Nodes, you must list the new nodes in the <filename>nodetype.dnt</filename>
		  file to expose them for use in the Designer.</para> 
	 <para>If you would like to assign an icon to a Frontend Node that you
		  create, use the <property>DesignerImageAttribute</property> to select an image
		  form the list of images used by the Designer.</para>
</chapter>
