<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<part id="DACDGUsing"> 
	 <partinfo><date role="LastMod">Wednesday, October 09, 2002 5:11:29
				PM</date>
	 </partinfo>
	 <title><indexterm><primary>Using the DAC</primary></indexterm>Using the
		  DAC</title> 
	 <partintro> 
		  <para>Part I of the DAC Developer's Guide contains an architectural
				overview of the Dataphor Data Access Components.</para> 
	 </partintro> 
	 <chapter id="DADDGUsingOverview"> 
		  <title>Overview</title> 
		  <sect1> 
				<title>Introduction</title> 
				<para>Components are classes that do not manifest themselves on a
					 user interface (non-visual), but instead perform "internal" behavior for the
					 application. Controls are are classes that are usually presented on the user
					 interface of the application (visual). When designing and application, both
					 components and controls can be visually prepared and manipulated from within
					 the Visual Studio .NET designer. The Dataphor Data Access Components (DAC) is a
					 set of components and Windows Forms controls that provide interactive access to
					 data housed in a database system.</para> 
				<para>The .NET Framework (and therefore Visual Studio .NET)
					 includes a data access paradigm called ADO.NET. The Dataphor Data Access
					 Components provide a complete alternative to ADO.NET, with some distinct
					 advantages. Some benefits of the DAC are most apparent when compared with
					 ADO.NET, while others are distinct for the industry.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGUsingDifferences"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>DAC versus
								ADO.NET</primary></indexterm>Differences From ADO.NET</title> 
				<para>ADO.NET and the DAC are fundamentally different in the way
					 that they buffer and navigate the data. ADO.NET requires the developer to
					 determine an adequate subset of data to retrieve from the DBMS into a buffer.
					 The developer then performs interaction and manipulation within the absolutely
					 indexed buffers. Then the developer determines how to appropriately post
					 updates to the DBMS. ADO.NET does not abstract or insulate the data source's
					 query language or capabilities. The DAC on the other hand performs the data
					 querying, buffering, and reconciliation automatically. Navigation in the DAC is
					 performed as relative positioning within what logically appears to be the
					 entire dataset. These differences are so fundamental that the DAC concepts
					 could not be built on top of ADO.NET without severely compromising the desired
					 architecture. Here are a few comparisons between ADO.NET and the Dataphor DAC: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>ADO.NET</entry><entry>DAC</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>Each different DBMS is queried using a
												different query dialect. Application logic must be re-created for each
												DBMS.</entry><entry>Accepts a single query dialect then emits whatever dialect
												is necessary to the backend DBMS.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>The developer must formulate queries
												that retrieve only a "reasonable" amount of data.</entry><entry>The DAC handles
												the end query formulation and automatically ensures appropriate quantities are
												fetched.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Controls are "loosly" bound to the
												dataset buffer through property binding.</entry><entry>Controls are made
												intrinsically data aware.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Reconciliation is facilitated manually
												by formulating parameterized update statements.</entry><entry>The DAC
												automatically manages buffer reconciliation including transactional
												implications.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Control data binding is based (by
												default) on control containership.</entry><entry>Controls are data bound
												independent from their containers.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Most data behavior only takes place at
												run-time.</entry><entry>Datasets can be activated and viewed both at run-time
												and design-time.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGUsingBenefits"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>DAC
								Benefits</primary></indexterm>Benefits</title> 
				<para>There are many benefits to using the DAC including: 
					 <itemizedlist> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Intrinsically data aware controls can react
									 intelligently to focus changes, dataset states, and formatting.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Controls are bound to datasets indirectly through
									 DataSource instances. This allows for existing forms to be easily attached to
									 different datasets regardless of control containership.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Controls report the number of rows that each
									 requires, so the dataset buffer size is dynamic (based on demand).</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>The DataView (dataset buffer) automatically
									 retrieves data into the buffer and updates the DBMS from the buffer.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Data aware user interfaces can be configured and
									 activated at design time within the Visual Studio .NET environment.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Controls and data components can be visually
									 connected and configured so very little coding is required to build data aware
									 applications.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
					 </itemizedlist></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGAdvancedBenefits"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>DAC Advanced
								Benefits</primary></indexterm>Advanced Benefits</title> 
				<para> 
					 <itemizedlist> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Single query dialect - The DAC can be attached
									 one of a variety of data sources, yet queries are formulated in a single
									 dialect and translated realtime into the appropriate dialect for the data
									 source. This allows for applications to be easily ported from one database
									 backend to another.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Query processor - If a particular data source
									 does not support certain functionality (i.e. scalar or relational operators)
									 the DAC will automatically pick up the query processing.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Updatable queries - Regardless of the expression
									 used by the dataset, the data can be updated. This is especially useful in the
									 case of joins and unions where views of that nature would not ordinarily be
									 updatable against the DBMS.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Navigational access - Dataset query is logically
									 formulated for the entire set of data. The DAC will automatically rewrite the
									 query underneith and fetch subsets of data.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Incremental search - Users can perform on-the-fly
									 "find nearest" type queries of even the largest underlying tables. As part of
									 the navigation access, the DAC will automatically re-query and fetch
									 appropriately to make such access effecient and tranparent.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Application transactions - Manipulations to
									 complex data relationship automatically participate in optimisticly concurrent
									 transactions so changes are all committed or rolled back when a "master"
									 dataset's change is accepted or rejected respectively.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
					 </itemizedlist></para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGInstallation"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>DAC
						  Installation</primary></indexterm>Installation</title> 
		  <para><indexterm><primary>Installation</primary></indexterm>The Data
				Access Components are relatively easy to install. For application design they
				can be installed into the Visual Studio .NET's "toolbox". For runtime
				deployment, the DAC assemblies can be copied into an application's local
				folder, or they can be installed into the Global Assembly Cache (GAC). For more
				general information on these concepts, see the MSDN documentation for the .NET
				Framework.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGStandardSetup"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>DAC Standard
								Setup</primary></indexterm>Standard Setup</title> 
				<para>To install the Data Access Components, run the setup.exe
					 program and follow the instructions.</para> 
				<para>The standard DAC setup performs the following: 
					 <itemizedlist> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Copies the DAC Assemblies (DLLs) to the directory
									 you chose during the install.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Installs the DAC Assemblies into the GAC.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Registers the Assemblies in the GAC with Visual
									 Studio so that they appear in the Form Designer ToolBox.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Copies the documentation help files and the
									 readme.rfd.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Creates links on start menu for docs and
									 readme</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Generates a GAC.licence file and places it in
									 CommonAppDataPath directory (which in this case is Documents and Settings\All
									 Users\Application Data\Alphora\Dataphor.)</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Copies DAERegisteredAssemblies.config, an
									 Assembly Map that contains Assembly Aliases for use in D4 code, to the Version
									 Specifice CommonAppDataPath directory (which in this case is Documents and
									 Settings\All Users\Application Data\Alphora\Dataphor\VersionNumber.)</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Creates registry key to instll path for use by
									 other programs. This is not used by the DAC components directly.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
					 </itemizedlist> </para> 
				<para>The components can also be installed on a machine manually
					 via the Deployment and then installed manually on the Visual Studio toolbox.
					 The assemblies must be placed into the GAC to be used from within Visual Studio
					 .NET.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDeployment"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>DAC
								Deployment</primary></indexterm>Deployment</title> 
				<para><indexterm><primary>Deployment</primary></indexterm>When
					 deploying the programs you have created which use the DAC, the following steps
					 need to be done. 
					 <itemizedlist> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>The DAC DLLs must be installed. They can be place
									 in the program directory or they can be installed into the GAC.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>The GAC.license file must be copied the the
									 CommonAppDataPath of the DAC, the same directory it was installed to
									 originally.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>The Assembly map (DAERegisteredAssemblies.config)
									 must be installed into the Version Specific CommonAppDataPath of the DAC, the
									 same directory it was installed to originally.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
					 </itemizedlist></para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGDataSessionComponents"> 
		  <title>DataSession Components</title> 
		  <para><indexterm><primary>DataSession</primary></indexterm>The
				DataSession components represents a logical connection with a data source.
				There are different 
				<classname>DataSessionBase</classname> descendant components for
				each backend data source, each prefixed with the name of the DBMS. To establish
				DAC data source connectivity place the appropriate DataSession component into
				the designer from the Visual Studio .NET toolbox (e.g. DB2DataSession for IBM
				DB2). To establish a connection to an instance of the Dataphor DAE, use a 
				<classname>DataSession</classname> component.</para> 
		  <para>Typically an application will only need one DataSession instance.
				This instance should be configured and created at application startup so that
				the DataSession instance is available for data connectivity from the various
				forms of the application.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDeviceDataSessionProperties"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Device-specific DataSession
								Properties</primary></indexterm>Device-specific DataSession Properties</title> 
				<para>Each specific 
					 <classname>DataSessionBase</classname> descendant has it's own
					 set of unique properties. The properties allow device specific settings to be
					 configured, such as connectivity information. See the reference part for
					 information about each specific DataSessionBase descendant's properties.</para>
				
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDatasessionProperties"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>DataSession
								Properties</primary></indexterm>DataSession Properties</title> 
				<para> To configure a DataSession component, configure the
					 <property>SessionInfo</property> and the <property>SessionName</property>
					 properties. The <property>SessionInfo</property> contains settings and
					 configuration parameters such as <property>UserID</property> and
					 <property>Password</property>. See reference information for the 
                     <!-- note: this link will be broken in the Stand Alone verison of this document -->
					 <ulink
					 url="Alphora.Dataphor.DAE.SessionInfo.html">SessionInfo</ulink> class for
					 details.</para> 
				<para>Setting the SessionName property registers the DataSession
					 with a static "global" list of application DataSessions so that DataViews can
					 be connected without being on the same design surface.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGActivateDataSession"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Activating the
								DataSession</primary></indexterm>Activating the DataSession</title> 
				<para>Activating the DataSession is done by setting the
					 <property>Active</property> property to <literal>True</literal> or calling the 
					 <methodname>Open</methodname> method at runtime. Activating the
					 DataSession causes it to establish a connection with the underlying data
					 source. If a connection cannot be made, and appropriate exception will be
					 thrown.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGDataViewComponent"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>DataView
						  Component</primary></indexterm>DataView Component</title> 
		  <para><indexterm><primary>DataView</primary></indexterm>The DataView
				component represents a dataset within a data source, based on a specific query
				expression. The DataView forms the core data manipulation component around
				which the other components in the DAC revolve. Through the DataView, data can
				be searched, retrieved, and modified. The DataView performs all data buffering
				transparently as navigation/searching occur.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGConnectingDataSession"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Connecting to the
								DataSession</primary></indexterm>Connecting to the DataSession</title> 
				<para>The DataView established connectivity with the underlying
					 data source through a DataSession instance. The DataView is associated with a
					 DataSession instance through the <property>Session</property> property. If the
					 DataSession associated with the DataView is not active when the DataView is
					 activated, it will be activated at that time (if possible).</para> 
				<para>The <property>Session</property> property can be set
					 directly, or it can be set indirectly through the
					 <property>SessionName</property> property. The SessionName property makes it
					 easy to link the DataView to DataSession instances that are located elsewhere
					 in the application.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGSettingExpression"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Setting the
								Expression</primary></indexterm>Setting the Expression</title> 
				<para>The DataView uses a query expression to retrieve it's logical
					 dataset. The expression is given in terms of a D4 or RealSQL expression which
					 returns a relation (table result). The query does not need to restrict the
					 dataset beyond what is logically desired, because the DataView will only
					 retrieve the sets of information that are necessary to populate it's internal
					 buffers.</para> 
				<para>The query dialect (D4 or RealSQL) used for the expression
					 depends on the <property>Language</property> property setting of the 
					 <classname>DataView</classname>, not the
					 <property>Language</property> property of the 
					 <classname>SessionInfo</classname> structure of the associated 
					 <classname>DataSession</classname> instance. See the D4 or
					 RealSQL reference for details on each language.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnAdornments"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Column
								Adornments</primary></indexterm>Column Adornments</title> 
				<para>The <property>Columns</property> collection property of the
					 DataView allows the specification of additional per-column definitions such as
					 defaults and constraints. Each column "adornment" is an instance of the
					 AdornColumnExpression class. The AdornColumnExpression has the following
					 "interesting" properties: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>ColumnName</entry><entry>Specifies the
												name of the column for which this adornment applies.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Default</entry><entry>Specifies the
												default value for the specified column of a newly inserted row.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Constraints</entry><entry>Contains a
												collection of 
												<classname>ConstraintDefinition</classname>
												classes specifying the list of constraints applicable to this column. A 
												<classname>ConstraintDefinition</classname>
												class has an <property>ExpressionString</property> property containing a valid
												D4 expression that evaluates to <literal>True</literal> if the value satisfies
												the constraint, <literal>False</literal> otherwise. Within the constraint
												expression, the value of the column is represented by an instrinsic variable
												called "<literal>value</literal>".</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>MetaData</entry><entry>MetaData is
												extra information about the column that might be useful to the application.
												This is a list of arbitrary identifier/string values.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGRowConstraints"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Row Constraints</primary></indexterm>Row
					 Constraints</title> 
				<para>Row-level constraints can be specified through the DataView's
					 <property>Constraints</property> collection property. Like column level
					 constraints, the row level constraints are manifest as a collection of 
					 <classname>ConstraintDefinition</classname> instances. Each 
					 <classname>ConstraintDefinition</classname> instance contains a
					 D4 expression that returns <literal>True</literal> if the constraint is
					 satisfied. For row level constraint expressions, the column values are
					 accessible by their names.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGSettingOrder"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Setting the
								Order</primary></indexterm>Setting the Order</title> 
				<para>Before the DataView can be activated, a sort order must be
					 established for the dataset. The order is set through the
					 <property>OrderString</property> property of the 
					 <classname>DataView</classname>. The order string takes the
					 following form: 
					 <programlisting>order {&lt;ne column name comma list&gt;}</programlisting>For example: 
					 <programlisting>order {LastName, FirstName}</programlisting></para> 
				<para>It should be noted that not only does the sort order affect
					 the logical ordering of the data, but incremental searching is also tied to the
					 sort order.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGActivatingDataView"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Activating the
								DataView</primary></indexterm>Activating the DataView</title> 
				<para>The DataView is activated by setting the
					 <property>Active</property> property to <literal>True</literal>, or calling 
					 <methodname>Open</methodname> at runtime.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDataManipulationStates"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Data Manipulation
								States</primary></indexterm>Data Manipulation States</title> 
				<para>At any given moment, a DataView is in one of the following
					 states: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>State</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Inactive</literal></entry><entry>The
												DataView is not active. In this state, data navigation and manipulation
												operations fail.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Browse</literal></entry><entry>The
												DataView is active and is in a navagable state. Data can be read, but not
												modified.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Insert</literal></entry><entry>The
												DataView is active and is positioned on an inserted (but not yet posted) row of
												data. The DataView is placed into <literal>Insert</literal> state by a call to
												the 
												<methodname>Insert</methodname> or 
												<methodname>Append</methodname> method, or
												by a call to 
												<methodname>Edit</methodname> when there
												are no rows in the dataset.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Edit</literal></entry><entry>The
												DataView is active and the row buffer at the current positioned can be edited.
												The DataView is placed into <literal>Edit</literal> state by a call to the 
												<methodname>Edit</methodname>
												method.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable> The state of a DataView can be determined by
					 examining the <property>State</property> property.</para> 
				<para>The state of the DataView is changed by activating,
					 deactivating, or by calling one of the state changing methods. The following
					 methods affect the state of the DataView: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Method</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Edit</literal></entry><entry>Places
												the DataView into <literal>Edit</literal> state, or does nothing if the
												DataView is already in that state. If the DataView is empty (0 rows), 
												<methodname>Edit</methodname> causes the
												DataView to go into <literal>Insert</literal> state.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Insert</literal></entry><entry>Places
												the DataView into <literal>Insert</literal> state. The temporary row buffer
												will appear at the position previously occupied by the active row.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Append</literal></entry><entry>Places
												the DataView into <literal>Insert</literal> state. The temporary row buffer
												will appear after the last row in the dataset.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Cancel</literal></entry><entry>Cancels
												any changed made to the data buffered by insert or edit and returns the
												DataView to the <literal>Browse</literal> state. If the DataView is already in
												<literal>Browse</literal> state, 
												<methodname>Cancel</methodname> does
												nothing.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><literal>Post</literal></entry><entry>Accepts
												any changes made to the data buffered by insert or edit and returns the
												DataView to the <literal>Browse</literal> state. If the DataView is already in
												<literal>Browse</literal> state, 
												<methodname>Post</methodname> does
												nothing.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGMasterDetailLinking"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Master/Detail
								Linking</primary></indexterm>Master/Detail Linking</title> 
				<para>DataView instances can be linked in such a way that one
					 instance presents a restriction (or detail) of information from another. This
					 is informally referred to as master/detail linking, where the "detail" is the
					 DataView being restricted and the "master" is the DataView from which the
					 restriction information is coming. As the master DataView is modified or
					 navigated, the detail DataView will reflect the new restriction
					 criteria.</para> 
				<para>Master/detail linking helps to automate data manipulation
					 tasks involving tables involved in a one-to-many relationship. For example, if
					 we have a Customer table and a CustomerPhone table and we allow there to be
					 many CustomerPhone rows for each Customer row, we may wish to present a user
					 interface that shows the list of CustomerPhone rows under the current Customer
					 we have selected. This would be accomplished by performing a master/detail link
					 between the DataView representing the CustomerPhone table and the DataView
					 representing the Customer.</para> 
				<para>Master/detail links are accomplished by setting the
					 <property>MasterSource</property> property of the detail DataView to a
					 DataSource instance that is attached to the master DataView. Additionally, the
					 <property>MasterColumnNames</property> and
					 <property>DetailColumnNames</property> are set to represent the column or
					 columns that are to be used to join the tables.</para> 
				<para>A master table must be active, have at least one row, and
					 have values for the columns that constitute the
					 <property>MasterColumnNames</property> in order for the detail DataView to be
					 in a Valid state. If an active detail DataView not in a Valid state, it will
					 behave similarly to when it is not Active. If a change occurs to the master
					 DataView which makes the detail DataView valid, the detail DataView will
					 automatically act normally for an Active DataView. To determine if a detail
					 DataView is in an invalid state, call the 
					 <methodname>IsValid</methodname> method.</para> 
				<para> When a detail table row buffer is inserted, the linked
					 detail table's columns are automatically defaulted to values from the
					 appropriate columns of the master table's active row.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGFilteringData"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Filtering
								Data</primary></indexterm>Filtering Data</title> 
				<para>Arbitrary filter conditions can be specified for a DataView
					 by setting the <property>Filter</property> property to a valid restriction
					 ("where clause") expression. If this value is changed while the DataView is
					 active, the DataView will automatically requery underneath to reflect the
					 change.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGNavigation"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Navigation</primary></indexterm>Navigation</title>
				
				<para>At any given moment, the DataView represents a single
					 "active" row position within the logical dataset specified by the
					 <property>Expression</property>. Navigating the active row in the DataView
					 takes place in a relative manner not based on an absolutely indexed position.
					 In other words, the DataView can be navigated to the beginning of the set,
					 forwards by a specific number of rows, or even to memorized bookmarks, but
					 there is no concept of row (or record) numbers. The ordering of the rows being
					 navigated is based on the sort order of the DataView.</para> 
				<para> There are two indicators, <literal>BOF</literal> and
					 <literal>EOF</literal>, that indicate when the DataView is at the beginning or
					 end of the logical dataset respectively. When initially opened, the
					 <property>BOF</property> property of the DataView will always be
					 <literal>True</literal>. The <property>EOF</property> property will return
					 <literal>True</literal> <emphasis>after</emphasis> navigating past the last row
					 of the dataset (not when navigating <emphasis>to</emphasis> the last row).
					 <property>EOF</property> will only be <literal>True</literal> upon activation
					 of the DataView if the dataset is empty. Just like <literal>EOF</literal>, once
					 the DataView has been navigated past the first row, the <literal>BOF</literal>
					 indicator will not be <literal>True</literal> until navigating
					 <emphasis>before</emphasis> the first row.</para> 
				<para>The following methods can be used to perform basic DataView
					 navigation: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Method</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry><methodname>First</methodname></entry><entry>Navigates
												the active row to the first row of the logical dataset. After this method is
												called, the <property>BOF</property> property will return
												<literal>True</literal>.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><methodname>Prior</methodname></entry><entry>Navigates
												the active row to the row immediately prior to currently active row, or, if the
												DataView is already situated on the first row, sets the BOF indicator.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><methodname>Next</methodname></entry><entry>Navigates
												the active row to the row immediately following to currently active row, or, if
												the DataView is already situated on the last row, sets the EOF
												indicator.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><methodname>Last</methodname></entry><entry>Navigates
												the active row to the last row of the logical dataset. After this method is
												called, the <property>EOF</property> property will return
												<literal>True</literal>.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><methodname>MoveBy</methodname></entry><entry>Navigates
												the active row a specific number of rows away from the currently active row,
												or, sets the BOF or EOF indicator appropriately.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGBookmarks"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Bookmarks</primary></indexterm>Bookmarks</title>
				
				<para>Bookmarks are used to memorize and recall specific active row
					 positions in the DataView. A bookmark is retrieved by getting the
					 <property>Bookmark</property> property; the position is restored by setting the
					 same.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGSearching"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Searching</primary></indexterm>Searching</title>
				
				<para>A DataView can be searched and navigated to specific rows.
					 This type of searching does not <emphasis>restrict</emphasis> the logical
					 dataset like the <property>Filter</property> or <property>Expression</property>
					 does, this search is navigational. Navigational searching takes place on the
					 columns specified in the sort order of the DataView.</para> 
				<para>Navigational searching is performed using the 
					 <methodname>FindKey</methodname> and 
					 <methodname>FindNearest</methodname> methods of the DataView. 
					 <methodname>FindKey</methodname> either locates the row by the
					 given criteria and returns <literal>True</literal>, or performs no navigation
					 and returns <literal>False</literal>. 
					 <methodname>FindNearest</methodname> positions the active row
					 on the row of the dataset that most closely matches the given criteria. 
					 <methodname>FindNearest</methodname> is particularly useful for
					 allowing the user to perform "incremental search" behavior.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGAccessingData"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Accessing Data
								Programmatically</primary></indexterm>Accessing Data Programmatically</title> 
				<para>Access to the data in the active row buffer can obtained
					 through the <property>Fields</property> collection of the DataView. Specific
					 Field class instances are retrieved from the <property>Fields</property>
					 collection either by their column name or their ordinal position in the
					 collection. The <property>Fields</property> collection can be enumerated and
					 also contains the standard collection properties such as
					 <property>Count</property>.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGFieldClass"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Field Class</primary></indexterm>Field
					 Class</title> 
				<para>The Field class contains the logic necessary to get and set
					 data values for individual columns within the active row. It also provides
					 information about the represented columns data type. Field instances are
					 obtained from the <property>Fields</property> collection of the
					 DataView.</para> 
				<para>Field data is typically read and written to using the AsXXX
					 properties (where XXX is the data type). Columns within a newly inserted row
					 will not have values yet, and attempting to read the field value will throw an
					 exception. To determine if a Field has a value, use the
					 <property>HasValue</property> property. If the DataView associated with the
					 Field instance is not already in an editing state (<literal>Edit</literal> or
					 <literal>Insert</literal>) when a Field value is changed, than the DataView
					 will automatically be placed in an editable state.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGDataSourceComponent"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>DataSource
						  Component</primary></indexterm>DataSource Component</title> 
		  <para><indexterm><primary>DataSource</primary></indexterm>The
				DataSource components provides a level of indirection between the DataView
				Component and the data-aware controls. The decisions regarding which controls
				are associated with what logical datasets is usually made when controls are
				placed on the form, but the actual association of a dataset with the form may
				not occur until runtime. The DataSource allows for forms to be easily "hooked
				up" to a DataView without connecting each control individually.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGAttachingDataView"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Attaching to the
								DataView</primary></indexterm>Attaching to the DataView</title> 
				<para>The DataSource is associated with a single DataView instance
					 through the <property>View</property> property. Any controls that are
					 associated with the DataSource instance are then indirectly associated with the
					 DataView instance.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGUsingDataSourceRuntime"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Using the DataSource at
								Runtime</primary></indexterm>Using the DataSource at Runtime</title> 
				<para>DataSource instances are often associated with DataView
					 instances at run time. This allows multiple forms to be attached to the same
					 logical dataset at runtime. For example, if there is a "browse" form shown for
					 the Customer table and the user selects "Edit..." to modify the currently
					 select Customer row: the edit form's controls could be easily associated with
					 the existing DataView instance on the browse form by attaching the DataSource
					 instance on the edit form to the DataView instance on the browse form.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGDBGridControl"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>DBGrid Control</primary></indexterm>DBGrid
				Control</title> 
		  <para>The DBGrid control visually represents data within the DataView
				in a tabular fashion. The DBGrid not only displays the currently active row of
				the DataView, but also as many other rows above or below the active row as
				space allows. The DBGrid also provides mechanisms to navigate the DataView. The
				DBGrid is a read-only control with the exception of boolean columns which can
				be represented with toggleable check boxes embedded on the DBGrid.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DADCGDBGridAppearance"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Appearance</primary></indexterm>Appearance</title>
				
				<para>The DBGrid draws a table of rows representing a subset (not
					 necessarily proper) of the DataView's dataset. The first row of the DBGrid
					 table is always the "header" containing the names of the columns whose values
					 are represented below. If the DBGrid is unable to display all columns in the
					 allotted space, it displays a horizontal scroll bar. A vertical scroll bar is
					 presented for row navigation within the dataset. </para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDBGridDataSource"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Attaching the Grid to the
								DataSource</primary></indexterm>Attaching the Grid to the DataSource</title> 
				<para>The DBGrid, like other data aware DAC controls, is associated
					 with a 
					 <classname>DataSource</classname> instance through the
					 <property>Source</property> property. When the DBGrid is linked to a DataSource
					 instance what is in turn linked to an active DataView instance, the DBGrid
					 automatically becomes "live" with data (whether in the Visual Studio .NET
					 designer or at runtime).</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDBGridColumns"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Setting the Grid
								Columns</primary></indexterm>Setting the Grid Columns</title> 
				<para>When attached to a live dataset, the DBGrid component
					 displays the columns of information specified by the
					 <property>Columns</property> collection property, and in the order they appear
					 in that collection. If no columns are explicitly given when the DBGrid instance
					 becomes active, the <property>Columns</property> collection is automatically
					 populated with default values from the DataView's data type information.</para>
				
				<para>The GridColumn class represents an individual column in the
					 <property>Columns</property> collection. The GridColumn class has several
					 properties including the following: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry><property>ColumnName</property></entry><entry>Name
												of the data column in the DataView to present. This does not have to be unique
												across the collection, or in other words, the same data column can be displayed
												multiple times.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><property>Width</property></entry><entry>Width
												in pixels of the presented data column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><property>Title</property></entry><entry>The
												text displayed in the header row for the column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><property>TextAlign</property></entry><entry>The
												horizontal alignment of data text displayed for the column of data.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><property>Color</property></entry><entry>Background
												color for data column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry><property>Visible</property></entry><entry>Whether
												or not the data column is currently visible.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
				<para>The GridColumn can also be descended from to provide unique
					 functionality. One such descendant is the CheckBoxGridColumn that renders a
					 check box control instead of the textual representation of the data. The
					 CheckBoxGridColumn can be configured as read-only through the
					 <property>ReadOnly</property> property.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDBGridNavigation"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Navigation</primary></indexterm>Navigation</title>
				
				<para>In addition to visual navigation capabilities, the DBGrid has
					 extensive keyboard support. The following is a partial list of supported
					 hotkeys: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Key</entry><entry>Description</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>Left</entry><entry>Scrolls to show the
												column just prior to the leftmost visible column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Right</entry><entry>Scrolls so that the
												second-to-leftmost column becomes the leftmost column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Ctrl-Left</entry><entry>Scrolls so that
												the leftmost column becomes the rightmost one.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Ctrl-Right</entry><entry>Scrolls so
												that the rightmost column becomes the leftmost one.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Ctrl-Alt-Left</entry><entry>Scrolls so
												that the first column is the leftmost column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Ctrl-Alt-Right</entry><entry>Scrolls so
												that the last column is the leftmost column.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Up, Down</entry><entry>Navigates to the
												prior or next row.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>PgUp, PgDn</entry><entry>Navigates to
												the prior or next page of rows.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Home, End</entry><entry>Navigates to
												the topmost or bottommost visible row in the grid.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Ctrl-Home,
												Ctrl-End</entry><entry>Navigates to the first or last row in the
												dataset.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGIncrementalSearchControl"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>Incremenatal Search
						  Control</primary></indexterm>Incremental Search Control</title> 
		  <para>The IncrementalSearch control facilitaties "find nearest" style
				navigational searching of the DataView. The IncrementalSearch control searches
				within one or more columns that make up the DataView's sort order. As the sort
				order of the DataView changes, the available search criteria also
				changes.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGIncrementalAppearance"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Appearance</primary></indexterm>Appearance</title>
				
				<para>There are several properties of the IncrementalSearch control
					 that effect it's appearance: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>TitleVSpacing</entry><entry>The space
												between the criteria controls and the vertically alligned titles.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>TopMargin</entry><entry>The space
												between the top of the control and the criteria controls.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>NoValueBackColor</entry><entry>The
												color used for criteria with no value (to differentiate between a blank value
												and no value).</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>InvalidValueBackColor</entry><entry>The
												color used for criteria to indicate that the search criteria is
												invalid.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>TitleAlignment</entry><entry>The
												relative alignment of the criteria titles.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGIncrementalSearchDelay"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Search Delay</primary></indexterm>Search
					 Delay</title> 
				<para>The IncrementalSearch control delays searching until a
					 specified amount of time after the most recent keypress has occurred. This
					 interval ensures that searching does not occur while the user is actively
					 typing search criteria. The delay interval is configurable by setting the
					 TimerInterval property to the number of desired milliseconds.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGIncrementalSearchColumns"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Incremental Search
								Columns</primary></indexterm>Incremental Search Columns</title> 
				<para>When the DataView is activated, or the sort order changes,
					 the IncrementalSearch control prepares search criteria for the columns of the
					 sort order. The display information for the search criteria is automatically
					 deduced from the DataView's column definitions or it can be specified through
					 the <property>Columns</property> collection property. The Columns collection
					 contains instances of the IncrementalSearchColumn class. It should be
					 emphasized that the list of Columns does not specify the search criteria for
					 the IncrementalSearch control; the search criteria is always tied to the sort
					 order of the DataView. The IncrementalSearchControl instances merely specify
					 formatting information for columns that <emphasis>may</emphasis> appear as
					 search criteria.</para> 
				<para>The IncrementalSearchControl contains the following
					 properties: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>ColumnName</entry><entry>The associated
												column name.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Title</entry><entry>The text to use for
												the title of the search criteria.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>TextAlign</entry><entry>The alignment
												of text within the search criteria editor.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>ControlWidth</entry><entry>The pixel
												width to use for the search criteria sub-control.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGIncrementalOrderLookup"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Order Lookup</primary></indexterm>Order
					 Lookup</title> 
				<para>The IncrementalSearch control contains a lookup "button" to
					 allow the user to change search criteria. The behavior of this button must be
					 specified by the control user and does nothing by default. To define specific
					 behavior for this button, attach an event to the
					 <property>OnOrderLookup</property> event.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGColumnControls"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>Column-Level
						  Controls</primary></indexterm>Column-Level Controls</title> 
		  <para>Besides the DBGrid control, the other controls in the DAC are
				column-level, in that they display the value of an individual column within the
				active row of the DataView. Many of the DAC controls are data-aware extensions
				of the regular Windows Forms controls included with the .NET Framework.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsDataSource"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Attaching Data Aware Controls to the
								DataSource</primary></indexterm>Attaching Data Aware Controls to the
					 DataSource</title> 
				<para>Each column-level control not only has a
					 <property>Source</property> property to associate the control with a 
					 <classname>DataSource</classname> instance, but also a
					 <property>ColumnName</property> property to designate the associated
					 column.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsStaticText"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Static Text</primary></indexterm>Static
					 Text</title> 
				<para>The DBText control displays the value of the column within
					 the active row as static (non-editable) text. DBText inherits the properties of
					 the 
					 <classname>Label</classname> control, including the ability to
					 align the text through the <property>TextAlign</property> property.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsTextBox"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>TextBox-style
								Controls</primary></indexterm>TextBox-style Controls</title> 
				<para>There are several controls that display information and allow
					 the editing of data in a text box. Each text box control allows the user to
					 uniquely edit data value as text. When focus leaves the control or when an
					 explicit update request is made from the DataView, the text box controls update
					 the field values of the DataView. The simplest such control is the 
					 <classname>DBTextBox</classname> control which descends from
					 the standard 
					 <classname>TextBox</classname> control. The DBIntegerTextBox
					 control is similar to the DBTextBox control except that it only accepts integer
					 values. The DBDateTextBox is another DBTextBoxBase descendant control that
					 facilitates editing dates.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsLookup"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Lookup
								Controls</primary></indexterm>Lookup Controls</title> 
				<para>There are a few controls that appear similar to a TextBox,
					 but also provide an elipsis button to allow the user to "look up" a value for
					 the column. When the lookup button is triggered, the OnLookup event is
					 raised.</para> 
				<para>The DBLookupTextBox control can encapsulate a user specified
					 control so long as it descends from DBTextBoxBase. By default, the
					 DBLookupTextBox encapsulates a DBTextBox control. The encapsulated control
					 class is specified through the <property>TextBoxClassName</property> property.
					 The DBDateLookup control is like a DBLookupTextBox except that it houses a
					 DBDateTextBox (by default) and provides a calendar lookup.</para> 
				<para>The DBIntegerScrollBox control also encapsulates a control,
					 but assumes that the edited value is integral and provides up and down
					 scrolling buttons and a scrolling slider to alter the value.</para> 
				<para>The DBLookupButton control provides an elipsis button for use
					 in looking up values that cannot be edited directly (like they can be with the
					 DBLookupTextBox). If the AutoNextControl property is True then focus is
					 advanced to the next control after the lookup takes place.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsRadioGroup"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Radio Group</primary></indexterm>Radio
					 Group</title> 
				<para>The DBRadioGroup provides a group box containing radio button
					 from which the user can choose the value for the data column. The following
					 properties are some that can be used to configure the behavior of the
					 DBRadioGroup: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>Items</entry><entry>The list of items
												to show as radio buttons.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Values</entry><entry>The associated
												data values for each of the radio buttons.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>ReadOnly</entry><entry>When
												<literal>True</literal>, the control cannot be used to modify the data
												value.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Enabled</entry><entry>When 
												<literallayout>False</literallayout>, the control cannot be focused or the data modified.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsCheckBox"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>CheckBox</primary></indexterm>CheckBox</title>
				
				<para>The DBCheckBox control facilitates the editing of boolean
					 data values. It's behavior is similar to the standard CheckBox control. The
					 DBCheckBox features an <property>AutoUpdate</property> property that specifies
					 whether changing the control's state in turn immediately updates the data
					 value, or whether updating is deferred until the control loses focus. If
					 AutoUpdate is <literal>False</literal>, changes made to the DBCheckBox's state
					 will be posted when the control loses focus or when the DataView explicitly
					 requests an update. If the DBCheckBox's state is updated and
					 <property>AutoUpdate</property> is <literal>True</literal>, the changed state
					 is posted after a possible delay (as specified by the
					 <property>AutoUpdateInterval</property> property).</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsImage"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Image</primary></indexterm>Image</title>
				
				<para>The DBImageAspect control displays an image from the database
					 while maintaining that image's aspect ratio. A new image value can be set by
					 the user through the clipboard keyboard shortcuts (Ctrl-V for paste) or
					 programmaticly through the <property>Image</property> property.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGColumnControlsTreeView"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Tree View</primary></indexterm>Tree
					 View</title> 
				<para>The DBTreeView control shows data in a hierarchical manner.
					 The following properties are available to configure the DBTreeView: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>LookupKeyColumnNames</entry><entry>Must
												be set to a key (column list string) that that identifies a node in the
												tree.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>LookupParentKeyColumnNames</entry><entry>Must
												be set to a key that corresponds with a node's parent identity.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>AutoRefresh</entry><entry>If
												<literal>True</literal>, the DBTreeView rebuilds itself when the data
												changes.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGNDAControls"> 
		  <title><indexterm><primary>Non Data-Aware
						  Controls</primary></indexterm>Non Data-Aware Controls</title> 
		  <para>Although the Dataphor DAC are certainly focused on providing
				complete and elegant data access and manipulation capabilites, there are also
				several controls that are not directly data aware. Some of these non data aware
				controls are in place to provide a base for a data aware counterpart.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGNDAControlsImage"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Image</primary></indexterm>Image</title>
				
				<para>The ImageAspect control displays an image similarly to the
					 standard Image control features certain "stretching" and display capabilities.
					 The ImageAspect control has a <property>StretchStyle</property> property that
					 controls how the image is resized to fit the control's dimensions. A useful
					 <property>StretchStyle</property> value is <literal>StretchRatio</literal>
					 which sizes the image to use the largest amount of space while maintaining
					 image's aspect ratio. The <property>Center</property> property specifies
					 whether a displayed images is centered within any unused space available within
					 the control. </para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGNDAControlsLookupPanel"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>LookupPanel</primary></indexterm>Lookup
					 Panel</title> 
				<para>The LookupPanel is a control container which includes an
					 elipsis button to allow the user to "look up" a valuepresumably for
					 the controls contained within the LookupPanel. The actual lookup behavior is
					 determined by the developer by attaching a handler to the
					 <property>OnLookup</property> event. This control is particularly useful for
					 creating lookups for values of a compound key (key with more than one column).
					 Keystokes made to controls placed in and isntance of the LookupPanel are
					 intercepted by the LookupPanel and made to invoke the lookup. In this way, the
					 LookupPanel makes child controls read-only except that they invoke a
					 lookup.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGNDAControlsRadioButtonGroup"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>RadioButtonGroup</primary></indexterm>Radio
					 Button Group</title> 
				<para>The RadioButtonGroup control provides a group of radio box
					 controls, each representing a specific data value. The following properties
					 affect the behavior of the RadioButtonGroup: 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Property</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>Items</entry><entry>Used to determine
												what radio button options are available within the group.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>CheckAlign</entry><entry>Specifies the
												position of the radio button sub-controls (left, center, or right).</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Appearance</entry><entry>Specifies
												whether or not the radio buttons show up as standard buttons or radio
												buttons.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>MarginWidth</entry><entry>The width of
												the margin between the control's inside boundary and the sub-controls.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>ButtonFlatStyle</entry><entry>Configures
												the "flat style" of the radio buttons (see the RadioButton class)</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>TextAlign</entry><entry>Specifies the
												alignment of the text protion of the radio buttons.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>SelectedIndex</entry><entry>The index
												of the currently selected radio button.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>Columns</entry><entry>The number of
												columns by which to align the radio buttons.</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGNDAControlsToolbar"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>ToolBar</primary></indexterm>ToolBar</title>
				
				<para>The ToolBar and ToolBarButton controls provide simple
					 horizontally or vertically aligned tool bar support. The ToolBar container will
					 accept any control as a child and will align it's child controls in a line (and
					 to fit the "bar"). The ToolBar button is similar to a standard Button except
					 that it does not accept focus.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
	 <chapter id="DACDGDataLink"> 
		  <title>DataLink</title> 
		  <para><indexterm><primary>DataLink</primary></indexterm>The DataLink
				control is the class used by the DAC to enable controls to become data aware.
				The DataLink provides a connection to the DataView, specifies the buffering
				requrements of the control (or other DataLink consumer), and provides event
				sinks necessary to respond to the DataView's data and state changes. It should
				be noted that although DataLinks are typically used for making controls data
				aware, the DataLink does not necessarily have to be hosted by a control. For
				example, the DataView itself uses a DataLink internally to connect to a master
				DataView.</para> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDataLinkPreparing"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Preparing the
								DataLink</primary></indexterm>Preparing the DataLink</title> 
				<para>The following actions may be taken to prepare a DataLink: 
					 <itemizedlist> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Create an instance of a DataLink class. This is
									 usually done in the constructor of the control.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Set the <property>Source</property> property. The
									 <property>Source</property> is usually configured as a pass through property of
									 the control (i.e. the control has a <property>Source</property> property that
									 gets and sets it's value from the DataLink instance's
									 <property>Source</property> property.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
						  <listitem> 
								<para>Set the BufferCount property. This property is
									 set to the number of rows that are concurrently accessed. For a grid-type
									 control, this is the number of rows that are currently visible in the grid. For
									 controls that only access the values of the currently active row this should be
									 left to one (1). This property should also be maintained (if necessary) as the
									 requirement for the number of buffered rows changes.</para> 
						  </listitem> 
					 </itemizedlist></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDataLinkAccessingData"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Accessing
								Data</primary></indexterm>Accessing Data</title> 
				<para>The DataLink consumer may access the data of the active row
					 of the DataView instance by directly reading values from the DataView's
					 <property>Fields</property> collection. A reference the the DataView instance
					 can be obtained from the <property>View</property> property of the DataLink. To
					 determine if the DataView instance is obtainable and active, use the DataLink's
					 <property>Active</property> property.</para> 
				<para>A DataLink consumer that requires access to more than one row
					 of the DataView can access the <property>Buffer</property> property. It is
					 important that if the DataLink consumer requires access to more than one row,
					 it sets the <property>BufferCount</property> appropriately. When accessing the
					 Buffer, the first buffer visible to the current DataLink is determined by
					 reading the <property>FirstOffset</property> property of the DataLink. The
					 currently active row of the DataView instance can be determined by accessing
					 the <property>ActiveOffset</property> property. The Buffer is a list of ViewRow
					 instances from which Row instances can be obtained. From a Row instance a
					 Scalar value can be obtained. From a Scalar value, a Conveyor can be used to
					 get the value in terms of a .NET data type. 
					 <programlisting>Alphora.Dataphor.DAE.Runtime.Data.Scalar LScalar = Link.Buffer[RowIndex].Row[ColumnIndex];
Text = LScalar.DisplayConveyor.GetAsString(LScalar);</programlisting>See the Dataphor DAE Developer's Guide for more
					 details.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDataLinkRespondingEvent"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>Responding to DataLink
								Events</primary></indexterm>Responding to DataLink Events</title> 
				<para>The DataLink receives notification when the state or data of
					 the DataView changes. These events can be noticed by descending from the
					 DataLink class and overriding certain methods or by hooking event handlers to
					 certain events. The following is a list of events that are available through
					 the DataLink. 
					 <informaltable> 
						  <tgroup cols="2"> 
								<thead> 
									 <row><entry>Method</entry><entry>Event</entry><entry>Description</entry>
										  
									 </row> 
								</thead> 
								<tbody> 
									 <row><entry>UpdateRow</entry><entry>OnUpdateRow</entry><entry>Invoked
												when the link should apply and changes that have not yet been posted to the
												active row. Update row is most commonly invoked before the DataView posts the
												data row to the dataset. Controls such as the DBTextBox allow changes to be
												made that aren't immediately saved to the DataView. This event indicates that
												such controls should immediately save such changes.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>RowChanged</entry><entry>OnRowChanged</entry><entry>Invoked
												when the active row has changes as a result of data edits (as opposed to
												scrolling, activation, etc.)</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>DataChanged</entry><entry>OnDateChanged</entry><entry>Invoked
												when the active row has changed as a result of anything other than data
												edits.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>FocusControl</entry><entry>OnFocusControl</entry><entry>Invoked
												when a validation error has occurred and a control associated with the error
												should be focused. The culprit field is passed as an argument.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>StateChanged</entry><entry>OnStateChanged</entry><entry>Invoked
												when the DataView changes edit states.</entry> 
									 </row> 
									 <row><entry>ActiveChanged</entry><entry>OnActiveChanged</entry><entry>Invoked
												when the DataView goes between the active and inactive states. This and the
												StateChanged events are also invoked in simulation, such as when the links
												between this DataLink instance and the DataView instance are changed (i.e. the
												DataSource instance is attached to another view).</entry> 
									 </row> 
								</tbody> 
						  </tgroup> 
					 </informaltable></para> 
		  </sect1> 
		  <sect1 id="DACDGDataLinkField"> 
				<title><indexterm><primary>FieldDataLink</primary></indexterm>Field
					 Data Link</title> 
				<para>The FieldDataLink class descends from DataLink and provides
					 features that are helpful when implementing controls that are associated with a
					 particular column of the dataset.</para> 
				<para>The constructor for the FieldDataLink takes a control
					 instance reference to be associated with the link. The control associated with
					 the FieldDataLink is obtainable through the <property>Control</property>
					 property. The control will automatically be focused when a FocusControl event
					 occurs.</para> 
				<para>The FieldDataLink has a <property>ColumnName</property>
					 property that, like the <property>Source</property> property, is typically used
					 in a pass-through fashion by the control. If any change occurs that may affect
					 the specific column specified by <property>ColumnName</property>, a
					 FieldChanged (and therefore OnFieldChanged) invocation occurs.</para> 
				<para>The FieldDataLink also has a <property>ReadOnly</property>
					 property that allows the data link to operate in read only mode. If the state
					 of the <property>ReadOnly</property> property changes, the UpdateReadOnly
					 virtual method is invoked, which in turn invokes the OnUpdateReadOnly
					 event.</para> 
				<para>The FieldDataLink has a <property>Modified</property>
					 property that can be used to trach whether or not the link has pending updates
					 to be made. To indicated that a change has been made, call the 
					 <methodname>Edit</methodname> method which will set the
					 modified flag as well an ensure that the DataView is in an editable state. To
					 undo the modified state, call 
					 <methodname>Reset</methodname> which clears the modified flag
					 an re-reads the links value from the DataView.</para> 
		  </sect1> 
	 </chapter> 
</part> 
