<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter id="DDGIntroduction"> 
	 <chapterinfo> 
		  <date role="LastMod">Saturday, March 02, 2002 2:28:39 PM</date> 
		  <revhistory> 
				<revision> 
					 <revnumber>1</revnumber> 
					 <date>Friday, June 07, 2002 9:43:38 AM</date> 
					 <revdescription> 
						  <para>DXC to DocBook</para> 
					 </revdescription> 
				</revision> 
		  </revhistory> 
	 </chapterinfo> 
	 <title>Introduction</title> 
	 <para>The 
		  <citetitle>DAE Developer's Guide</citetitle> describes the Dataphor
		  Data Access Engine architecture and provides complete reference information.
		  This manual covers intermediate to advanced topics such as a description of the
		  DAE's query processing architecture and information on extending the DAE. This
		  manual assumes familiarity with fundamental Dataphor concepts and techniques.
		  For in introduction to Dataphor, see the 
		  <citetitle>Dataphor User's Guide</citetitle>.</para> 
	 <sect1 id="DDGWhatsInThisManual"> 
		  <sect1info> 
				<revhistory> 
					 <revision> 
						  <revnumber>1</revnumber> 
						  <date>May 28, 2002 9:33:09 AM MDT</date> 
						  <revdescription> 
								<para>DXC to DocBook</para> 
						  </revdescription> 
					 </revision> 
				</revhistory> 
		  </sect1info> 
		  <title>What's In This Manual?</title> 
		  <para>This manual contains three parts, as follows:</para> 
		  <para> 
				<itemizedlist mark="bullet"> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para> 
								<citetitle>Part I</citetitle> </para> 
						  <para>"Application Development" describes the Dataphor DAE
								from the perspective of application development. This includes detailed
								coverage of the logical model in which the developer describes the data model
								and "business rules" of the application. This logical application description
								is independent of the interpretation provided by the implementation. This part
								is important for Application Developers and Database Administrators, but is
								also essential for those wishing to understand Dataphor.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para> 
								<citetitle>Part II</citetitle> </para> 
						  <para> "Implementation Architecture" describes the
								mechanisms and techniques used to implement a system based on the logical model
								described in Part I. Details about the architecture of the Dataphor DAE are
								provided in order to utilize and extend its capabilities. This part will be
								interesting for systems developers wishing to extend the DAE, or for
								application developers who wish to better understand the inner workings of the
								DAE.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para> 
								<citetitle>Part III</citetitle> </para> 
						  <para> "Reference" provides a detailed reference for both
								the logical and physical (or implementation) aspects of the DAE. It contains
								class definition documentation, language specifications and other essential
								reference information.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
				</itemizedlist> </para> 
	 </sect1> 
	 <sect1 id="DDGManualConventions"> 
		  <sect1info> 
				<revhistory> 
					 <revision> 
						  <revnumber>1</revnumber> 
						  <date>May 28, 2002 9:33:09 AM MDT</date> 
						  <revdescription> 
								<para>DXC to DocBook</para> 
						  </revdescription> 
					 </revision> 
				</revhistory> 
		  </sect1info> 
		  <title>Manual Conventions</title> 
		  <para>Unless otherwise noted, when the text in 
				<citetitle>Part I</citetitle> of this manual uses the term
				"object," it refers to items in the DAE catalog, not objects in the
				object-oriented sense. Because 
				<citetitle>Part II</citetitle> discusses object-oriented objects
				extensively, the text will be explicit when mentioning DAE catalog
				objects.</para> 
	 </sect1> 
	 <sect1 id="DDGPrerequisites"> 
		  <sect1info> 
				<revhistory> 
					 <revision> 
						  <revnumber>1</revnumber> 
						  <date>May 28, 2002 9:33:09 AM MDT</date> 
						  <revdescription> 
								<para>DXC to DocBook</para> 
						  </revdescription> 
					 </revision> 
				</revhistory> 
		  </sect1info> 
		  <title>Prerequisites</title> 
		  <para>The material in this manual builds on the assumption that the
				reader has some familiarity with the basic components of the Dataphor DAE as
				introduced in the Dataphor User's Guide. Some familiarity with basic
				programming concepts is also assumed.</para> 
		  <para> 
				<itemizedlist mark="bullet"> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para><citetitle>Part I</citetitle> of this manual includes
								an overview of database management concepts and techniques, as well as a D4
								language guide and a description of the overall architecture of the DAE.
								General understanding of current application development processes and tools
								will help in comprehending the concepts in this part.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para><citetitle>Part II</citetitle> contains class
								definitions, which may require familiarity with modern Object-Oriented
								Programming (OOP) concepts--particularly as implemented by the .NET Framework.
								Examples are provided in C#, though because of the multi-language nature of the
								.NET Framework, the same concepts apply in other .NET languages.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
				</itemizedlist> </para> 
	 </sect1> 
	 <sect1 id="DDGAdditionalResources"> 
		  <sect1info> 
				<revhistory> 
					 <revision> 
						  <revnumber>1</revnumber> 
						  <date>May 28, 2002 9:33:09 AM MDT</date> 
						  <revdescription> 
								<para>DXC to DocBook</para> 
						  </revdescription> 
					 </revision> 
				</revhistory> 
		  </sect1info> 
		  <title>Additional Resources</title> 
		  <para>Additional information may be obtained from the following
				sources:</para> 
		  <para> 
				<itemizedlist mark="bullet"> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para> 
								<link role="cref" linkend="DataphorUsersGuide">Dataphor
									 User's Guide</link> contains information about the overall purpose of Dataphor
								and the role of the Dataphor Data Access Engine.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para>Texts such as 
								<citetitle>An Introduction to Database
									 Systems</citetitle> by C. J. Date (Addison Wesley Longman) contain information
								about the Relational Model and its significance.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						  <para>The.NET Framework MSDN documentation, included with
								the .NET Framework SDK, provides information about the technology on which the
								Dataphor DAE is built.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
				</itemizedlist> </para> 
	 </sect1> 
</chapter> 
